export const GEOGRAPHYA2011 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. The scale of the map in statement form is",
A: "One centimetre on the map represents one kiolometre on the ground",
B: "Two centimetres on the map represents one kilometre on the ground.",
C: "Three centimetres on the map represents one kilometre on the ground.",
D: "Four centimetres on the map represent one kilometre on the ground.",
answer: "D. Four centimetres on the map represent one kilometre on the ground.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. The highest point on the map is slightly above",
A: "250m",
B: "350m",
C: "550m",
D: "650m",
answer: "D. 650m",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. The contour interval on the map is",
A: "25m",
B: "50m",
C: "150m",
D: "200m",
answer: "B. 50m",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The feature marked Z is a/an",
A: "Spring",
B: "Meander",
C: "Ox-bow lake",
D: "Delta",
answer: "C. Ox-bow lake",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. PAPAWA is a",
A: "Gap town",
B: "Defence town",
C: "Mining town",
D: "Recreational town.",
answer: "A. Gap town",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. The cultivation of rice can be practiced in",
A: "North eastern part of the map.",
B: "North western part of the map.",
C: "South eastern part of the map.",
D: "South western part of the map.",
answer: "C. South eastern part of the map.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Which of the following is an example of a linear settlement?",
A: "Etulo",
B: "PAPAWA",
C: "Keh",
D: "Adoga",
answer: "C. Keh",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. The distance along River Omar from Adoga to Etulo is",
A: "3km",
B: "5km",
C: "20km",
D: "25km",
answer: "B. 5km",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Which of the following is correct?",
A: "Keh can be seen from Stub.",
B: "Keh is on a lower elevation than Etulo.",
C: "PAPAWA performs less function than Etulo.",
D: "Adoga and Etulo are intervisible.",
answer: "D. Adoga and Etulo are intervisible.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. The bearing of Keh from PAPAWA is",
A: "025°",
B: "125°",
C: "225°",
D: "320°",
answer: "C. 225°",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. The planet that revolves around the sun in a clockwise direction is",
A: "Mercury",
B: "Mars",
C: "Uranus",
D: "Pluto",
answer: "C. Uranus",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Equinoxes occur on",
A: "March 21st and September 23rd",
B: ". June 21st and September 23rd",
C: "December 23rd and September 23rd",
D: "June 3rd and march 21st",
answer: "A. March 21st and September 23rd",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. Which of the following is not part of the solar system?",
A: "Sun",
B: "Venus",
C: "Earth",
D: "Star",
answer: "D. Star",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. Which of the following types of sedimentary rocks is paired with wrong texture?",
A: "Sand — coarse particles",
B: "Clay — very fine particles",
C: "Gravel — large and rounded particles",
D: "Silt — coarse and angular particles",
answer: "C. Gravel — large and rounded particles",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. Rocks formed as a result of changes in temperature and pressure or both are called",
A: "Sedimentary rocks",
B: "Metamorphic rocks",
C: "Plutonic rocks",
D: "Igneous rocks",
answer: "B. Metamorphic rocks",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Which of the following types of rocks is associated with stalactites?",
A: "Sandstone",
B: "Clay",
C: "Basalt",
D: "Limestone",
answer: "D. Limestone",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. All the following are surface features of Karst regions except",
A: "Stalagmites",
B: "Dolines",
C: "Grikes",
D: "Gorges",
answer: "A. Stalagmites",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. Earthquake shock is greatest at the",
A: "Epicenter",
B: "Sides of the epicenter",
C: "Origin",
D: "Sides of the focus",
answer: "A. Epicenter",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Which of the following may occur at the boundary of tectonic plates?",
A: "Waterfalls",
B: "Tornadoes",
C: "Thunderstorm",
D: "Earthquakes",
answer: "A. Waterfalls",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The physical transfer of soil materials from one layer by draining water or capillary water downward is",
A: "Calcification",
B: "Leaching",
C: "Humification",
D: "Illuviation",
answer: "B. Leaching",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. Which of the following is not relevant in physical weathering?",
A: "Temperature changes",
B: "Accumulation of salt crystal in rock",
C: "Frost shattering",
D: "Alternate wetting and drying",
answer: "B. Accumulation of salt crystal in rock",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. The quantity of water that sinks into the ground to form underground water depends on the following except",
A: "Pore spaces",
B: "Joints in the rocks",
C: "Run-off",
D: "Faults in the rocks",
answer: "C. Run-off",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. Which of the following lakes is formed by tensional forces in the earth’s crust?",
A: "Lake Bosomtwe",
B: "Lake Chad",
C: "Lake Malawi",
D: "Lake Tana",
answer: "D. Lake Tana",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The dry dusty winds that blow across West Africa are predominant in",
A: "February, March, April",
B: "May, June, July.",
C: "August, September, October.",
D: "November, December, January.",
answer: "D. November, December, January.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. Which of the following conditions will prevent the formation of deltas?",
A: "Absence of lakes in the course of the river.",
B: "Presence of a steep upper slope.",
C: "Presence of a strong tidal current at the mouth of the river.",
D: "Presence of several tributaries.",
answer: "C. Presence of a strong tidal current at the mouth of the river.",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Sea waves are normally caused by the action of",
A: "Rainfall",
B: "Strong wings",
C: "Abrasion",
D: "Earth’s revolution",
answer: "B. Strong wings",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The most common and the effective agent of erosion in the arid regions is",
A: "Sea",
B: "Wind",
C: "Running water",
D: "Rain",
answer: "B. Wind",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. Sandy deserts are usually referred to as the",
A: "Hamada",
B: "Erg",
C: "Badland",
D: "Wadis",
answer: "B. Erg",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Diurnal temperature range is the difference between the",
A: "Maximum and minimum temperatures of the day.",
B: "Maximum and minimum temperatures of the month.",
C: "Minimum and maximum temperatures for a season",
D: "Average daily and monthly temperatures.",
answer: "A. Maximum and minimum temperatures of the day.",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. Places of equal rainfall values are joined by lines called",
A: "Isoneph",
B: "Isohyets",
C: "Isotherm",
D: "Isohaline.",
answer: "B. Isohyets",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. The plants that cannot glow in areas of either too much or too little water are called",
A: "Hydrophytes",
B: "Xerophytes",
C: "Mesophytes",
D: "Heliophytes",
answer: "B. Xerophytes",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Which of the following is not true of tropical grassland?",
A: "They formed a belt round the tropical rainforest north and south of the Equator.",
B: "They are found on the western side of Madagascar.",
C: "The typical trees include acacia, silk, cotton, locust beans and baobab.",
D: "The trees look evergreen throughout the year.",
answer: "D. The trees look evergreen throughout the year.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Which of the following is a living element of the natural environment?",
A: "Fungi",
B: "Rocks",
C: "Water",
D: "Atmospheric gas",
answer: "A. Fungi",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Undercutting of rocks by wind blow blast will produce",
A: "Deflation hollow",
B: "Rock pedestals",
C: "Self dunes",
D: "Exfoliation domes.",
answer: "B. Rock pedestals",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Soil conservation is aided by",
A: "Overgrazing",
B: "Over cultivation",
C: "Strip cropping",
D: "Deforestation.",
answer: "C. Strip cropping",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. Which of the following is not a factor of population growth?",
A: "Birth rate",
B: "Death rate",
C: "Population density",
D: "Migration",
answer: "C. Population density",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. Rural settlements are characterized by all the following except",
A: "Small area coverage",
B: "Few social amenities",
C: "Secondary activities",
D: "Primary activities",
answer: "C. Secondary activities",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Two or more large urban centres that have grown towards each other and eventually merged but maintained their individual identities is called",
A: "Isolated settlement",
B: "Village",
C: "Town",
D: "Conurbation",
answer: "D. Conurbation",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Which of the following resources is non renewable?",
A: "Air",
B: "Water",
C: "Petroleum",
D: "Forest",
answer: "C. Petroleum",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. Areas degraded during mining of minerals could be recovered by",
A: "Irrigation system",
B: "Land reclamation",
C: "Deforestation",
D: "Volcanicity",
answer: "B. Land reclamation",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. The cultivation of a single crop on a large area of land using machines is called",
A: "Plantation agriculture",
B: "Bush fallowing",
C: "Arabic farming",
D: "Shifting cultivation",
answer: "A. Plantation agriculture",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. One relative advantage of road transport over rail transport is that it",
A: "Is use to carry bulky goods",
B: "Provides door to door services.",
C: "is slower.",
D: "Is cheaper.",
answer: "B. Provides door to door services.",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. Road transportation has a major advantage over other modes of transportation because of its",
A: "Flexibility",
B: "Convenience",
C: "Short distance hauls",
D: "Long distance hauls.",
answer: "A. Flexibility",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. The processing of raw materials into finished products is called",
A: "Local crafts",
B: "Manufacturing",
C: "Mining",
D: "lumbering",
answer: "B. Manufacturing",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. The act of cutting down trees for commercial purposes is",
A: "Timbering",
B: "Lumbering",
C: "Forestry",
D: "Farming.",
answer: "B. Lumbering",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Which of the following contribute most to the abundance of fish in the Sea of Japan?  \nI. Plenty of plankton in the sea  \nII. Meeting of warm and cold current  \nIII. Broad expanse of deep sen water  \nIV. Turbulence of the sea.",
A: "I and III",
B: "I and II",
C: "I and III",
D: "II and IV",
answer: "B. I and II",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. The Congo Basin is covered mainly by the",
A: "Temperate forest",
B: "Monsoon forest",
C: "Tropical rainforest",
D: "Coniferous forest",
answer: "C. Tropical rainforest",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the following is not an attribute of African rivers?",
A: "Volume is constant with season",
B: "Presence of debris",
C: ". Presence of rapids and waterfalls",
D: "Shallowness of rivers.",
answer: "A. Volume is constant with season",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. Which of the following is not a reason for the low volume of trade among Tropical African countries?",
A: "They produce almost identical commodities.",
B: "They prefer trading with their former colonial masters.",
C: "There are very many trade agreements between them",
D: "Their port facilities are well developed.",
answer: "D. Their port facilities are well developed.",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The biggest island of Africa is",
A: "Madagascar",
B: "Cape Verde",
C: "Canaries",
D: "Sao Tome",
answer: "A. Madagascar",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},


]